

GERMAN INSTITUTE OF DEVELOPMENT AND SUSTAINABILITY (IDOS), RESEARCHEF

Tulpenfeld 6 53113 Bonn, Germany

Semuhi.Sinanoglu@idos-research.de | # semuhi.github.io | Semuhi | Semuhi | semuhi | semuhisinanoglu | semuhi

### **Short Bio**

I am a researcher at the German Institute of Development and Sustainability (IDOS). I study how autocrats employ and justify repression in polarized contexts, and politically control key social groups during economic downturns. I also contribute to the computational and experimental methodological tools in political science research.

## **Education**

#### **Degree programs**

University of Toronto, CA 2018-24

**PhDc in Political Science** 

- Thesis | For Better for Worse: Autocrats and their Business Allies during Sovereign Debt Crises
- Committee Members: Lucan Way, Kanta Murali, Michael Donnelly

Koc University, TR 2014-17

2009-14

**MA in International Relations** 

• Thesis | Varieties of Capitalism in the Middle East & North Africa: A Comparative Perspective

Bogazici University, TR
Double Major with Political Science & International Relations & Economics

Non-degree programs & training

University of Michigan, USA Summer 2019

**ICPSR Summer Program** 

• EITM-certified courses: Advanced Bayesian Statistics

McGill University, CA 2017-18

**Graduate Research Trainee** 

Harvard Kennedy School, USA Spring 2017

**Executive Education: Leadership, Organizing, and Action** 

Columbia University, USA Spring 2013

**Exchange Program** 

## **Academic Research**

### **Peer-reviewed publications**

- 2024. Out of sight, out of mind: The impact of lockdown measures on sentiment towards refugees. **Journal of Information Technology & Politics** 21(2): 166-75 (with Amir Abdul Reda and Amine Aboussalah).
- 2024. Mobilizing the masses: Measuring resource mobilization on Twitter. **Sociological Methods and Research** 53(1): 153-92 (with Amir Abdul Reda and Mohamed Abdalla).
- 2022. Containing ethnic conflict: Repression, co-optation, and identity politics. **Comparative Politics** (54)5: 765-86 (with Ceren Belge).

#### **Under review**

- 2023. Taming a paper tiger? Public support for the repression of the business elite. OSF Preprint.
- 2022. Divided at home, divided abroad? Affective polarization and political tolerance among migrants (with Selin Kepenek).

#### **Working papers**

- 2024. Climate disasters exacerbate polarization. Could cross-partisan outreach help? (with Michael Donnelly).
- 2024. Tax audit as authoritarian repression during sovereign debt crises.
- 2024. Autocrats and their business allies: The informal politics of co-optation and defection.
- 2023. Different types of soft propaganda and support for cross-border operations (with Michael Donnelly).

#### **Work in progress**

- 2023. The determinants of defection in civil wars: Survey experiments with rebel groups in Myanmar (with POST-COR).
- 2023. The prosecution of heads of state and democratic backsliding (with Seva Gunitsky).

#### **Selected presentations**

- 2024. Climate disasters exacerbate polarization: Could cross-partisan outreach help? CEU Democracy Institute DRD Annual Workshop: Breaking the Dynamics of Political Polarization; APSA Annual Conference, Montreal (with Michael Donnelly).
- 2021. Divided at home, divided abroad? APSA Annual Conference, Seattle; ECPR General Conference, September (with Selin Kepenek).
- 2019. Containing ethnic conflict: Repression, co-optation, and identity politics. ISA, Toronto (with Ceren Belge).
- 2014. A typology of welfare regimes in the Middle East and North Africa. ECPR General Session, Warsaw.

June 18, 2024 Semuhi Sinanoglu · Résumé 1

#### Other research experience

- 2022. Preventing civil war recurrence (with POSTCOR Lab).
- 2020. Protests, resource curse, and economic diversification (with Jacques Bertrand).

### **Research Grants**

2023	<b>Reserch Grant</b> by the IHS for online survey experiments in Turkey	Virginia, USA
2022	<b>Hayek Fund</b> by the IHS for my research on the business support for autocracies	Virginia, USA
2022	Travel, Research, Engagement Grant by POMEPS to fund my research on depolarization	DC, USA
2021	<b>Priority Theme Small Grants Fund</b> by FGAP to fund my research on depolarization	Berkelev USA

## Fellowships and Affiliations \_\_\_

-	
2022-23 Regional Manager at the Digital Society Project	ND, USA
2022-23 Graduate Associate at the POSTCOR Lab	Toronto, CA
2022-23 Trudeau Centre Fellow in Peace, Conflict, and Justice at Munk School	Toronto, CA
2022 Oskar Morgenstern Fellowship by the Mercatus Center	Virginia, USA
2019-22 Non-resident Junior Fellow at Massey College	Toronto, CA
2017-18 <b>Resident Junior Fellow</b> at Jeanne Sauvé Foundation	Montreal, CA
Human Rights & Governance Fellowship by the Open Society Foundation	Budapest, HU
2012 Young Scholar at the Global Relations Forum	Istanbul, TR

## Awards and Scholarships\_

2023	Outstanding TA Award by the University of Toronto	Toronto, CA
2021-23	Mary H. Beatty Scholarship by the University of Toronto	Toronto, CA
2022	M. W. Donnelly Fellowship in Political Economy by the University of Toronto	Toronto, CA
2020	Ontario Graduate Scholarship (OGS) by the Province of Ontario	Toronto, CA
2020	The Morimitsu Inaba Doctoral Scholarship by the University of Toronto	Toronto, CA
2019	The Ranjit Kumar Graduate Scholarship by the University of Toronto	Toronto, CA
2019	ICPSR Scholarship by the EITM	Ann Arbor, USA
2014	<b>Graduate Scholarship</b> by the Scientific and Technological Research Council of Turkey	Ankara, TR
2009	Outstanding Success Scholarship by the Turkish Educational Foundation	Istanbul, TR

## Other Selected Publications

- 2021. A time of crisis and opportunity: Digitizing SMEs in Turkey. Istanbul: Turkish Enterprise and Business Confederation & CIPE.
- 2021. COVID Impact Assessment Report. Istanbul: Turkish Enterprise and Business Confederation.
- 2021. Otoriter rejimlerde bürokrasi: Sadık mı layık mı? [Bureaucracy under authoritarianism: Loyal or competent?] *Daktilo1984*, February 15.
- 2019. We need a new conservative party in Turkey for regime transition. *The Jerusalem Post*, March 31.
- 2018. Memlekete dönmek [Returning home]. Birikim, November 12.
- 2018. Building a policy school that has real social impact. *Policy Options*, February 28.
- 2018. Socially inclusive Fourth Industrial Revolution: Fostering youth employment in the Middle East and North Africa. In *Realizing Youth Potential in the Mediterranean: Unlocking Opportunities, Overcoming Challenges*, edited by Lorenzo Kamel & Asli Selin Okyay: 101-12. Rome: IAI Research Studies.
- 2018. Op-eds published on civil society in Turkey on Civic Pages.
- 2017. Death & politics: the burial of a Kurdish woman in Turkey. *openDemocracy*, October 4.
- 2017. Review of Steven Cook's False Dawn: Protest, Democracy, and Violence in the Middle East. *Turkish Policy Quarterly* (Summer): 107-11.
- 2017. Parti ebed müddet: Bir siyaset teknolojisi olarak Yeni Osmanlıcı TRT dizileri [The eternal party: New Ottomanist TV series as a political technology]. *Birikim*, March 30.
- 2016. 5 disturbing facts about living under occupation. Middle East Monitor, August 22.
- 2016. Tackling the Syrian refugee crisis: Prospects & challenges. *Turkish Policy Quarterly* (Spring): 123-30 (with E. Arslan & I. Taner).
- 2015. Development Analytics. Improvement of basic services delivery for the poor in the OIC member countries. Ankara: COMCEC.
- 2014. Development Analytics. Supply and demand for child care services in Turkey. Washington, DC: World Bank.
- 2011. Youth who make the future. openDemocracy, September 23.
- 2009. Ein kristallener leuchter ist die zeit am Istanbul Lisesi: 125 jahre mit dokumenten (1884 -2009). Istanbul: IEL Educational Foundation (with L. Deniz & I. Buyukkal).

## **Teaching Experience**

University of Toronto, CA 2020 - 2024

**Course Instructor** 

- The political economy of economic crises
- Autocrats of the world: International politics of authoritarianisms
- Politics in the Middle East

**University of Toronto, CA** 

2018 - current

**Teaching Assistant** 

- Comparative Politics | Democracy, Dictatorship, War and Peace; Democratization in Modern Europe; State, Society and Power
- Political Economy | Politics of Development; Global Political Economy: Policy and Analysis; U.S. Government and Politics
- *Methods* | Introduction to Quantitative Reasoning; Using Data to Understand Politics and Society; Public Opinion and Voting; Thinking Through Research Design (grad-level); Statistics for Political Scientists (grad-level)

Trinity College, CA 2019 - 2022

**Academic Don** 

Koc University, TR 2014-2016

**Teaching Assistant** 

## **Professional Experience**

### **German Institute of Development (IDOS)**

2024-current

Researche

• I work on a project that focuses on the global trends of polarization and autocratization.

Maidan, CA 2019-2023

Co-founder

Maidan forecasts elections and protests using big data analytics.

CityInclusive, CA 2017-19

Co-founder

Canada's Smart Cities Challenge presented an opportunity for cities to make themselves socially inclusive. On our
digital platform, we documented and analyzed the works of Canadian cities as they went through the process of developing applications for the Challenge. CityInclusive team was also recognized as futurists in residence at the Concordia
University's Institute for Urban Futures.

Co-Opinion Network, TR 2015-17

**Founding President** 

Co-Opinion is a policy-oriented network that mobilizes more than 30 stakeholder institutions in 6 countries across
the Middle East & North Africa to tackle youth unemployment in the wake of 4th Industrial Revolution. The network
achieved cross-sectoral collaboration between the region's several business associations and youth-led NGOs. The
network organized annual summits, capacity development workshops, and stakeholder meetings in Belgium, Italy,
Lebanon, Morocco, Tunisia, and Turkey, with support by established organizations such as the Rockefeller Foundation
and the Open Society Foundation.

Development Analytics, TR 2014-15

**Social Policy Researcher** 

• I assisted with quantitative and geo-spatial analysis, and desk reviews for two policy reports delivered to the World Bank and COMCEC.

# **Public Speaking**

- 2022. ChatGPT Hayatimizi Nasil Etkileyecek? [How will ChatGPT impact our lives?]. Istanbul: TUIC (December).
- 2019. Podcast: Görsel Kültürün Politikası [The Politics of Visual Culture]. Istanbul: Medyapod (February).
- 2018. Future of Turkey's Youth in a Time of Turmoil. Washington, DC: Middle East Institute (December).
- 2018. Middle Powers: Saudi Arabia. Toronto: Global Citizens Dialogue (November).
- 2018. On Spaces and Rights: Refugee Settlement Policies in Lebanon & Turkey. Montreal: McGill University (March).
- 2018. Socially Inclusive Fourth Industrial Revolution. Rome: Italian Ministry of Foreign Affairs (March).
- 2017. Youth Cooperation under an Authoritarian Regime. Istanbul: Konrad Adenauer Stiftung (April).

# **Selected Trainer Experience**

- 2023. The politics of authoritarianism: A short introduction. Toronto: University of Toronto (October).
- 2021. An Introduction to spatial Analysis using R. Toronto: University of Toronto (March).
- 2017. Organizational Development & Management: Digital Security in the Age of Hyper-Surveillance. Istanbul: Co-Opinion (April-June).
- 2017. Design Lab: Preventing & Countering Violent Extremism. Istanbul: Co-Opinion & Hollings Center for International Dialogue (April).

# **Selected Events and Trainings**.

- 2023. IHS Discussion Colloquium: Polarization, Pluralism, and Democracy. VA: Institute for Humane Studies (May).
- 2021. IHS Discussion Colloquium: Polarization and Contemporary Political Life. VA: Institute for Humane Studies (November).

June 18, 2024 Semuhi Sinanoglu · Résumé

- 2018. Making Powerful Brand Storytelling; Business Model Canvas; Theory of Change & Design Thinking; VOX Method: Public Speaking; Social Impact Assessment; Making Persuasive Business Recommendations. Montreal: Jeanne Sauvé Foundation.
- 2017. Leadership Academy: Strengthening NGOs. Germany: Friedrich Naumann Stiftung (March).
- 2017. CDN Study Session. Budapest: Council of Europe (January).
- 2016. Middle East & North Africa Regional Meeting. Nicosia: PUGWASH (November).
- 2016. Prospects for Job Generation in the Middle East. Italy: Rockefeller Foundation Bellagio Center (October).
- 2016. Young Peacebuilders Forum. The Hague: UNOY (September).
- 2016. ChangemakerXChange. Lisbon: Ashoka Foundation (August).
- 2016. Sulaimani Forum. Sulaimani: American University of Sulaimani (March).
- 2015. T-20. Antalya: TEPAV (November).
- 2012. Winter School. Ankara: Center for Strategic Research (January).

### Service.

- 2023 **Reviewer**, APSR
- 2022 **Search Committee for Middle Eastern Politics**, grad. rep. at the University of Toronto.
- 2020-23 Quantitative Methods Research Cluster, co-organizer at the University of Toronto.
- 2022 **APSA General Conference**, discussant & panel organizer.
- 2021 APSA General Conference, discussant.
- 2019 **Search Committee for Quantitative Methods**, grad. rep. at the University of Toronto.
- 2019 The Khashoggi Killing and the Future of US-Saudi Relations, event organizer.
- 2018-20 **Comparative Autocracy Research Cluster**, organizer at the University of Toronto.

### Skills

**Language:** Turkish (native), **English** (fluent), **German** (Sprachdiplom-C1-2009), **Arabic** (beginner)

**Software:** R, Qualtrics, Java, STATA, ArcGIS, Python, Premiere Pro Gallup Clifton Strengths: Developer, Individualization, Input, Learner, Empathy